那么我们今天这节课就是要建立一种安全的压缩功能。
So our goal for this segment is to build
secure compression functions. So
压缩功能是一种无碰撞散列函数。这是一种会在我们关注
compression functions are collision
resistant. So just to remind you where we
Merkle Damguard结构（从哈希结构而来，比其稍复杂的可以处理更大的输入）时
are we looked at this Merkle Damguard
construction which takes a little
提醒我们进度如何的功能。
compression function and builds from it a
hash function for much, much larger
我们研究这个定理因为事实上如果小的碰撞函数
inputs. We proved this cute theorem that
in fact if a little compression function
是抗碰撞的并运用了Merkle Damguard函数
is collision resistant then plugging in
into the Merkle Damguard construction
我们就可以得到一个相对于哈希函数适用于更大的输入的抗碰撞的函数。
gives us a collision resistant hash
function for larger inputs. So now in this
所以今天我们就是要大体上建立一个抗碰撞的压缩函数。
segment our goal is basically to build a
compression function that is collision
接下来我们看几种函数。
resistant. So we're going to see a couple
of constructions. And so the first
那么第一个问题就是，我们能不能从现有的基础中建立压缩函数呢？
question that comes to mind is well, can
we build compression functions from
特别要说，我们在建立块加密上做了很多研究，
primitives that we already have? In
particular, we spent a lot of work to
现在的问题就是我们能否从块加密中建立压缩函数。
build block cyphers and the question is
can we build compression functions from
答案是肯定的。下面我来告诉大家这是怎样做到的。
block cyphers. And the answer is yes. And
let me show you how to do it. So assume we
假设有一个基于N比特的块特定的块加密，
have a certain block cypher here that
operates on N bits blocks, so the input is
也就是说输入和输出都是N比特。
an N bits, output is N bits. And then
there's this classic construction called a
根据我在这里写出来的这种经典函数——Davies-Meyer函数，
Davies-Meyer construction which I wrote
down in symbols here. Basically says that
它告诉我们，在已知信息块和链接变量的情况下，
what you would do is, given the message
block and the chaining variable, all we do
我们要做的就是将信息块用作密码来解密链接变量。
is we encrypt the chaining variable using
the message block as the key. And then we
接着我们对输出再做一次异或，这可能看起来有点奇怪，
kind of do one more xor on the output. So
this might seem a little bizarre, because
因为链接变量是一种看起来完全在敌手的控制之下的东西。
remember the message block is something
that's completely under the control of the
他在尝试寻找碰撞，所以他会选择任何他需要的信息块。
adversary. He's trying to find the
collision so he can choose the message
同时，我们在将这个信息块用作块加密中的密码。
blocks however he wants. And yet we're
using this message block as a key into a
然而，我们可以认为这种函数，
block cypher. But nevertheless, we can
argue that this construction, at least
至少当E被视为一种理想函数时，我们可以认为它尽可能的做到了抗碰撞。
when E is what's called an ideal cypher,
we can argue that this construction is in
现在我们来总结一下。上面的定理是说，
fact as collision resistant as possible.
So let me state the theorem. The theorem
如果E是一个理想的块加密，意思是它是个在从0,1到N到0,1到N
states that, as I said, if E is an ideal
block cypher, meaning that it's a random
的随机排列中的随机集合。
collection of K random permutations from
01 to the N to 01 to the N. Then under
在这种假设下，E 就是一个理想的块加密，事实上，
that assumption that E's an ideal block
cypher, in fact, finding the collision for
在压缩函数H下寻找碰撞花费的时间是2的2~N倍。
this compression function H takes time,
two to the N over two. In particular, we
而且，我们可以看出寻找碰撞的人必须评估加密和
can show that anyone who is finding
collisions has to evaluate the encryption
解密函数至少2分之2~N次。
and decryption functions at least 2 to
the N over 2 times. And if you think
并且如果你仔细想想这意味着什么，因为压缩函数的输出只有N字节，
about what that means, since the output of
this compression function is only N bytes
我们知道通用的生日攻击法可以在2分之
long, we know that there's always a
generic birthday attack that finds
2至N次数中寻找碰撞。所以这个定理说
collisions in time 2 to the N over 2.
So basically this theorem says that this
这种抗碰撞函数已经做到了尽可能的抗碰撞。
collision resistant function is as
collision resistant as possible. We can
我们可以用生日攻击法在2分之2~N的次数寻找碰撞，
find the collision in time 2 to the N
over 2 using the birthday attack but
而且没有算法能比这种函数做到更多次。
there is no algorithm that will do better
than 2 to the n over 2. So this
所以这种在实际中是一种非常常见的碰撞函数在
is actually a very common compression
function used in collision resistance
哈希抗碰撞中，运用了Davies-Mayer的SHA的函数。
hashing in fact of a SHA
functions all used Davies-Mayer. It turns
它说明在Davies-Mayer函数中有一些特别的东西做到抗碰撞。
out that there is something special about
the Davies-Mayer construction that
如果你尝试着猜测函数那么很可能你会
makes collision resistant. If you just try
to guess the construction very likely you
因为某些不抗碰撞的东西而停止。接下来的问题是，
will end up with something that is not
collision resistant. And so let me ask you
假设我们按照刚刚说的样子定义了碰撞函数，
the following puzzle. Suppose we actually
define the compression function as
即我们要做的就是用现信息块作为密钥来解密链接变量H。
follows, namely all we do is we encrypt
the chaining variable H using the current
那么区别就是我们在Davies-Mayer中对H做了异或，
message block as the key. So the
difference is that we dropped this 'xor' H
我们只是忽略了它。所以问题不在这里。
in Davies-Mayer, we simply ignored it. So
it's not there. And the puzzle for you
问题在于，这个碰撞函数事实上并不能抗碰撞。
is show me that this compression function
then is actually not collision resistant.
因此，我们尝试建立一个碰撞，即
So, let's see, so we're trying to build a
collision, namely a distinct pair of HM
特定的一对（H，M）与（H'，M‘）在后面会提到的H函数下发生碰撞。
and H' M' that happen to collide
under this later function H. And my
我给大家提出的问题就是，你如何做到？
question to you is how would you do it? So
I'm already going to tell you that you're
你们会任意地选择H，M和M'。
going to choose H, M, and M'
arbitrarily. The only requirement is that
唯一的要求是M和M‘是不同的。接下来的问题是，如何构造
M and M' are distinct. And then my
question is, how would you construct an H'
一个会产生出碰撞的H‘。最优选择也是最简单的办法是
that would cause a collision to pop
out? So the answer is the first choice and
观察我们回应加密函数是否对两边都用了M’。
an easy way to see it is if we apply the
encryption function using M' to both
那么我们就得到了M‘用来回应H’的E，没错。
sides. Then we get that this is basically
E of M' applied to H', right.
这是我们运用M‘对左边做了回应加密得到的东西。
this is what we get by applying encryption
using M' to the left hand side. And
如果我们使用M'对右边暗示加密
if we imply encryption using M' to
the right hand side, the decryption
解密操作符将被抵消，那么我们剩下的仅仅是加密的(M,H)
operator cancels out and we simply are
left with the encryption of M, H, which is
这就是我们想找到的碰撞。你会发现
exactly the collision that we wanted to
find. So there. You can see that it's
主要是运用解密函数D，而为压缩函数建立一个碰撞是非常容易的
basically by using the decryption function
D, it's very easy to build collisions for
事实上，Davies-Meyer算法并不是独一无二的
this compression function. Now I should
tell you that in fact Davies-Meyer is not
有其他方法可以建立基于块加密的耐碰撞压缩函数
unique. There are other ways to build
collision resistant compression functions
比如这里就有一个称作Miyaguchi Preneel模式结构
from block ciphers. For example, here's a
method called Miyaguchi Preneel. Miyaguchi
Miyaguchi Preneel模式结构被用于我们先前看到的涡流哈希函数
Preneel actually is used in WHIRLPOOL hash
function that we saw earlier. Here is
这里是另一个得到耐碰撞压缩函数的方法
another method that happens to result in a
collision resistant compression function.
有12个像这样的变式运用了异或并且将这些变式
And there are twelve variants like this
playing with XORs and placing the
运用于不同层事实上就得到了一个耐碰撞机制
variables in different slots that will
actually give a collision resistant
但是有太多太多变式，像我们
mechanism. But there are also many, many
variants of this like we saw in the
在之前的难题中见到过的，但却不是耐碰撞的。
previous puzzle that are not collision
resistant. So here's. Another example,
所以这里给了另一个不是抗碰撞的例子，我将把它作为课后题给你们
that's not collision resistant. And I'm
gonna leave it as a homework problem to
你们需要给这个结构找到一个碰撞
figure out a collision for this
construction. So now, basically, we have
现在我们已经有了全部成分来写出256位哈希函数
all the ingredients to describe the
[inaudible] 256 hash function. I'll tell
这就是我们之前见到的Merkel-Damgard结构
you that it's a Merkel-Damgard
construction, exactly as the one that we
它运用了Davies-Mayer压缩函数
saw before. It uses a Davies-Mayer
compression function. And so the only
唯一的问题是，Davies-Mayer压缩函数的潜在分组密码是什么?
question is, what's the underlying block
cipher for Davies-Mayer? And that block
分组密码叫做SHACAL-2。我只是告诉你这是参数，它使用了512比特的密钥
cipher is called SHACAL-2. And I'll
just tell you it's parameters. It uses a
这里的密钥是从信息分组中得到的
512 bit key. And remember the key is taken
from the message block. So, this is really
这就是信息分组的本质，这样正好就是512位
what the message block is. And it so
happens to be 512 bits. Which means the
SHA-256将一次处理512位的输入信息
SHA-256 will process its input
message 512 bits at a time. And in the
分组密码的分组大小为256位。这些就是链接变量
block size, for this block cipher is
256 bits. And these are the chaining variable.
这里就是H i-1。它将成为连续链接变量
So this would be H i-1.
And this would be successive chaining variable.
现在你对SHA-256的运作有了全面的认识
So now you have a complete
understanding of how SHA-256 works.
SHACAL-2密码的模块我就不在这里详说了
Module of this cipher SHACAL-2 I'm not going to describe here.
就像我所说，一类压缩函数是通过分组密码建立的
So as I said, one class of compression functions is built from block cyphers. It
turns out there's another class of
这就意味着有另一类压缩函数是通过数论难题建立的
compression functions that's built using
hard problems from number theory, and I
我将简短地举一个例子。我们说这些压缩函数是可证明的
want to very briefly show you one example.
And we call these compression functions
是因为如果你可以找到一个碰撞
provable because if you can find the
collision on this compression function
你就能够解决一个非常棘手的数论难题
then you're going to be able to solve a
very hard number theoretic problem which
如果这个数论难题是非常棘手的
is believed to be intractable. And as a
result, if the number theory problem is
那么由此产生的压缩函数就被证明是耐碰撞的
intractable, the resulting compression
function is provably a collision
这里解释了压缩函数的工作原理
resistant. So here's how this compression
function works. Basically we're going to
我们将选择一个大的分组，就像700位数字
choose a large prime piece, so this is a
gigantic prime, something like 700 digits,
2000位。然后再在1到P中选择两个随机值U和V
2,000 bits. And then we're going to
choose two random values, U and V, between
现在定义压缩函数如下
one and P. And now let's define the
compression function as follows. It takes
它从0到p-1中得到两个数，并将输出0到p-1中的一个数
two numbers between 0, and p-1,
and it's gonna output one number between
那么压缩比就为1/20,
and  p-1. So it's compression
ratio is 2 to 1. And takes two
从0到p-1的范围中得到两个数，并输出一个数
numbers. And outputs one number. In the
range 0 to p-1.
可以通过双求幂运算得到，并计算U的H次方与V的N次方的乘积
And it does it basically by computing double exponentiation. It
computes u to the H times v to the n.
这个定理事实上
And the theorem, which, right now, I'm just
gonna state as a fact. This fact actually
只需要一个相当简单的证明，我们将在
turns out to be fairly straightforward to
prove, and we're gonna do it later on when
数量理论课程部分进行证明。如果你可以找到
we get to the number theoretic part of the
course. The fact is, that if you can find
一个关于此压缩函数的碰撞，那么你就可以解决一个在数论中
a collision for this compression function,
then you can solve a standard heart
被称作谨慎日志问题的核心问题。每个人都觉得谨慎日志非常难
problem in number theory called a discreet
log problem. Everyone believes discrete
那么得到的压缩函数就能证明是耐碰撞的
log is hard, and as a result, this
compression function is provably collision
你可能会问我为什么人们现实中不用这个压缩函数
resistant. So you might ask me why do
people not use this compression function
为什么我们不将它用于SHA-256
in practice. Why would we not use this for
SHA-256? And the answer is that this
因为相比你得到分组密码，它的性能非常缓慢
gives very slow performance in comparison
to what you get from a block cipher. So
所以这并不能真正用于任何压缩函数
this is not really used for any
compression functions. However, if for
如果因为某些原因你仅仅只是想知道，MAC或是标志。仅有一长信息
some reason you really only want to, say,
MAC or sign. Just one long message, and
你有一整天来解决它，那么你可以用这样的压缩函数去解决。
you have a whole day to do it, then
certainly you can use this type of
即使它运行非常缓慢，但你能得到一个耐碰撞的数据
compression function. And even though it's
slow, you'll get something that's provably
那么这一段就结束了
collision resistant. Okay, so that's the
end of this segment. And now we're finally
我们在之后的课程中终于准备讲HMAC了。
ready to talk about HMAC, which we're
gonna do in the next segments.